<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="GMF Tutorial">
   <intro>
      <description>
         This tutorial guides you through the definition, mapping, and generation of a graphical editor for mindmaps using GMF.<br/><br/>To start working on this cheatsheet, click the &quot;Click to Begin&quot; button below.<br/><br/>This cheatsheet is complemented by detailed steps in the online GMF Tutorial.
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item title="Create a New Project" dialog="true" skip="true">
      <description>
         First, we&apos;ll create a new project to hold our models.<br/><br/>The default name will be set and a new &apos;model&apos; folder will be created for you, if you use the &quot;Click to Perform&quot; button below.
      </description>
      <action class="org.eclipse.gmf.internal.doc.ui.actions.OpenProjectWizardAction" pluginId="org.eclipse.gmf.doc.ui" confirm="false" param1="org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap">
      </action>
   </item>
   <item title="The Domain Model" dialog="false" skip="true">
      <description>
         At this point, you can either copy the provided mindmap.ecore or mindmap.xsd model into the &apos;model&apos; folder, or use the ECore diagram to model it from the diagram provided online.<br/><br/>Next, we'll create a new mindmap.genmodel and generate the model and edit code.
  		<br/><br/>The following steps are required:
  		<br/><br/>1. Right-click the mindmap model file and select <b>New... | Other... | Eclipse Modeling Framework | EMF Model</b> and use the defaults of the wizard to create a new mindmap.genmodel.
  		<br/><br/>2. Select the Mindmap package below the root of the genmodel and in the Properties view, change the <b>Base Package</b> property to <b>org.eclipse.gmf.examples</b>.
  		<br/><br/>3. Right-click on the root of the genmodel and select <b>Generate Model Code</b> followed by <b>Generate Edit Code</b>.
  		<br/><br/><br/>Now, with our domain model ready, we can begin our graphical definition.  Press &quot;Click to Complete&quot; below.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item title="Create a Graphical Definition" dialog="true" skip="true">
      <description>
         In a graphical definition, you will define figures, nodes, compartments, connections, etc.<br/><br/>Using the wizard, we can get started on our graphical definition by examining our domain model. Use the &quot;Click to Perform&quot; button to get started.
		<br/><br/>The following steps are required:
  		<br/><br/>1. In the wizard, select the &apos;org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap/model&apos; as the parent folder for your mindmap.gmfgraph model.
  		<br/><br/>2. The second page of the wizard has a <b>Browse</b> button that should easily find our mindmap.ecore model.  For Diagram Element, select the Map class.
  		<br/><br/>3. The last page of the wizard gives us options for those features found in our domain model (node, link, or label).  For now, uncheck all but the &apos;Topic&apos; element as a node, its &apos;name&apos; attribute as a label, and the &apos;subtopics&apos; relationship as a link.
      </description>
      <action class="org.eclipse.gmf.internal.doc.ui.actions.OpenGraphWizardAction" pluginId="org.eclipse.gmf.doc.ui" confirm="false" param1="mindmap.gmfgraph">
      </action>
   </item>
   <item title="Create a Tooling Definition" dialog="true" skip="true">
      <description>
         Our graphical definition for our editor will need tooling to be useful. We will again use a wizard to get started by examining the domain model. Use the &quot;Click to Perform&quot; button to get started.
  		<br/><br/>The following steps are required:
  		<br/><br/>1. Again, select the &apos;model&apos; folder to hold the mindmap.gmftool model.
  		<br/><br/>2. On the second page we will locate our mindmap.ecore file as before, and select our Map class for the Diagram Element.
  		<br/><br/>3. On the last page, uncheck all but our &apos;Topic&apos; element and the &apos;subtopics&apos; relationship.
      </description>
      <action class="org.eclipse.gmf.internal.doc.ui.actions.OpenToolWizardAction" pluginId="org.eclipse.gmf.doc.ui" confirm="false" param1="mindmap.gmftool">
      </action>
   </item>
   <item title="Create a Mapping Definition" dialog="true" skip="true">
      <description>
         Now it&apos;s time to map our graphical elements and their tools to our domain model. Use the &quot;Click to Perform&quot; button to get started.
     	<br/><br/>The following steps are required:
  		<br/><br/>1. Again, select the &apos;model&apos; folder to hold the mindmap.gmfmap model.
  		<br/><br/>2. On the second page, we find our mindmap.ecore model is already selected. Choose the Map class for the canvas and press <b>Next</b>.
  		<br/><br/>3. On the third page, we find our mindmap.tool model is already loaded. Keep the defaults and press <b>Next</b>.
  		<br/><br/>4. On the fourth page, we find our mindmap.gmfgraph model is already loaded. Keep the defaults and press <b>Next</b>.
  		<br/><br/>5. On the last page of the wizard, examine the mappings determined by the wizard. For now, remove all but &apos;Topic&apos; in the Nodes list, and &apos;subtopics&apos; in the Links list. Press <b>Finish</b> when you&apos;re done.
      </description>
      <action class="org.eclipse.gmf.internal.doc.ui.actions.OpenMapWizardAction" pluginId="org.eclipse.gmf.doc.ui" confirm="false" param1="org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap/model" param2="mindmap.gmfmap" param3="platform:/resource/org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap/model/mindmap.ecore" param4="platform:/resource/org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap/model/mindmap.gmfgraph" param5="platform:/resource/org.eclipse.gmf.examples.mindmap/model/mindmap.gmftool">
      </action>
   </item>
   <item title="Create a Label Mapping" dialog="false" skip="true">
      <description>
         We&apos;ll manually create a label mapping for our Topic element using the following steps: 
         <br/><br/>1.Right-click the &apos;Node Mapping&apos; below the only &apos;Top Node Reference&apos; in the mapping model and create a new <b>Feature Label Mapping</b>.
         <br/><br/>2.In the properties view, select the <b>TopicName</b> diagram label.
         <br/><br/>3.Select the <b>name</b> attribute for the <b>Features</b> property.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item title="Code Generation" dialog="false" skip="true">
      <description>
         The last model you&apos;ll need will be transformed from the mapping model and contain those properties needed to generate the source code for your editor.<br/><br/>To produce the generator model, right-click on your mindmap.gmfmap file and select <b>Create generator model...</b>.<br/><br/>You may want to browse this model and examine its properties. There are many options to consider when generating code. When you&apos;re ready, right-click the mindmap.gmfgen file and select <b>Generate diagram code</b>.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item title="Running the Diagram" dialog="false" skip="false">
      <description>
         You are ready to test the diagram. From the <b>Run | Run...</b> menu, create a new <b>Eclipse Application</b> runtime configuration and launch your diagram using the default settings.<br/><br/>You&apos;ll need to create a project and then a <b>New | Examples | Mindmap diagram</b>. Explore the functionality provided, including layout, alignment, selection, etc.
      </description>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>
